[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[Music]
Hello, good day, good evening everybody
and welcome back to the Ask Abijit show.
I hope everybody is doing great.
Everyone's doing fantastic. It's great
to see you all. I would like to thank
all of you who wrote all those comments
yesterday and today as well in response
to my video. I really appreciate it. I
could not respond to everybody's
comments individually, but thank you so
much everybody. uh whatever everything
you said it really means a lot to me and
I would also like to tell you that next
week uh in the ask show which will
happen next weekend we will do a history
special I will take questions from the
comments about history only it's been
very geopolitics focused the past few
months but yeah next week we'll we'll do
a history special next weekend so the
questions from the comments I'll take
questions about history today I've
chosen lots of geopolitics questions
anyway let's see who is there on the
live chat I can see somi join from
Jaipur. Bat first, Chaitanya Mangula,
Manuja, Sanidya Kumar, happy Rakaan to
everybody. Happy Raabandhan. Rashmir
from Rajasthan, Deep Binakdas, Suhas,
Reddi, Suprainda, Nungar, Johan, hello
sir, Shri Ramundra, Rahan, Namaste,
Swami, Jane, Koshik, Mukharji, Mr. Jam,
Raj, Radi, James Pangam, good evening.
Ashit KS, say my name. Well very
breaking bad isn't it? Pamel nandi
meangaswas
happyan sana satish binayakdas ain
srihari arjunep sam triati aish panchal
from Calgary
uh Aush Singhes
ki uh who else do we have? Um
uh I can see Nikil Eliat from New
Zealand. Well good to see you sir. Uh
Ashit Vladimir Putin is there. Ji Ram
Mr. Vladimir Putin, Sagar Katkam, Vidant
Kulkarni, Hitan Shua from Gujarat. Good
evening. Uh, Geopolitical Dubai from
Indor. Hello. Samart again. Aayush
Aayush Aayoshi Uttori. Namaste. Shri
Javaharal Nehuj is there. Namaste G.
Prane Paul from Kolkata. Good evening.
Sager Torat. Who else do we have?
Yashagna, Anupam, Bora, Saneda Kumar,
and Roida live from West Bengal. Utsavv
Khatri from Ahmedabad, Anerod Pay, Savia
Set, Sam Kulkarni,
Ding Pegu from Assam, Shashank Koshik,
Uju
uh and so many so many sir, so many
people. Thank you so much all of you for
being on the live chat. I will yeah take
it off the screen now and let's take
some questions. Let's begin with uh the
questions that I have picked. Lots of
these. Let's take as many as possible
today.
So we have a couple of questions from
Mclavvin and Pipal. The IIAF, the Indian
Air Force has announced that we downed
multiple F-16 fighter planes during the
operation Synindur. And the timing is
interesting. The this was announced
today.
Uh the IIAF chief Salai has officially
revealed details of shooting down five
Pakistani jets and one Awax aircraft
during operation zindur along with F-16s
destroyed on the ground. What's the
strategic significance of revealing this
now 3 months after the event? What does
the timing indicate? Very interesting
timing. Very interesting timing. So the
IIF knew what it had achieved. It knew
that it had shot down X number, let's
say five, I think it was five that was
said, right? Five Pakistani fighter
planes of various kinds. One AVAC. I
mean these rumors have been around for
quite some time, but it was never
officially confirmed by the IIAF. Uh so
one AVAC, five Pakistani fighter jets,
uh multiple F-16s destroyed on the
ground, many runways destroyed, many
aircraft hangers and many air many air
bases hit and so on. But this point
about five fighter planes being shot
down by the S5 S400 system that hasn't
been officially confirmed until now. So
we the Indian Air Force has revealed
this today. That's what it's been 3
months roughly since operation Sindor
took place, right? June to May to June,
June to July. Yeah. Three three months
now. Uh 3 months ago it was happening
operation tendur it was it was the
second day 3 months ago. So um yeah we
have chosen to to to
announce this today. What does it mean?
Why wasn't this announced earlier? The
Pakistanis were running wild with their
propaganda that they shot down 700
Indian aircraft and God knows what not
what not, right? And their propaganda
was being amplified by the western
media.
And we knew that we had done all this.
We had shot down five fighter planes and
caused so much so and so quantum of
destruction on the ground. F-16s
destroyed and so on. We did not speak
about it. Why? Looks like
looks like the government did not want
to
um put the Americans in a delicate
position. They do not want to upset the
Americans because there was the
possibility of a trade deal, right?
Those days the trade deal there was
there was there were multiple deadlines
the Americans had imposed upon us for
agreeing to to a trade deal with them.
So because there was the possibility of
a trade deal, a good mutually beneficial
trade deal. That's why it looks like the
government chose to suppress this
information.
That's what it looks like. and the
Pakistanis were allowed to run run wild
rampage with their propaganda and the
western media obviously amplified it
right so that's what it looks like the
government was it it did not want to
offend or upset the Americans
and put them in a delicate position
where they they have to reveal where
it's revealed that their ass their
assets were destroyed
and where you have F-16s you also have
American personnel on the ground if
India destroyed multiple F-16s on the
ground.
It means that it's possible that
American personnel were hit because we
know that wherever you have Pakistani
F-16s, which are obviously American
aircraft bought from the US, the
Americans have personnel on the ground
who always 24 by7 babysit the F-16s and
never let the aircraft out of their
sight.
Right? So, uh,
all of this happened and we kept quiet
about it. We did not reveal it so that
the Americans aren't displeased. Now
that Trump has launched an all-out
offensive against India.
Now that he has launched an all allout
offensive against India, he's cozying up
with Pakistan. He's inviting the
Pakistani fellow Aim Mun for a second
visit and so on. So it's clear that the
Trump the Trump administration the Trump
regime has decided to go all in on
Pakistan.
So now and they they've imposed 50%
tariffs on India. They're threatening
way more tariffs, maybe 500% tariffs,
what not.
So I mean if the gloves are off, let
them be off. So it looks like that's why
this was uh revealed today, right? Uh
but it's it's kind of a shame that uh
the Pakistanis were allowed to just run
wild with the propaganda and uh yeah I
mean lots of people have ended up
believing that Pakistan scored
significant successes against India
because of the propaganda that was
amplified by the western media. Anyhow
so that's that's the thing. So this
indicates what does this indicate big
picture? a deterioration
in India US relations
and this indicates that India is no
longer concerned about offending or not
offending the US. Looks like the gloves
are off and looks like uh relations have
have gone back backwards 30 40 50 years
like the days of the old cold war the n
the 20th century cold war India and the
US were always on opposing sides those
days. So whatever strategic trust may
have been built up over the past few uh
decades everything seems to have eroded
now and we are back to square one. So
India US relations are really rocky
right now. This is what it ind this
indicates.
Okay. Miranka Seekhar Biswas says the is
the US by extending a second state visit
to the Pakistani guy the dictator Aim
Munir the de facto dictator Aim the head
of the military um is the US by
extending a second state visit to this
guy to this individual subtly nurturing
a future military musharaf to safeguard
its strategic interests in Pakistan
absolutely absolutely so the US is not
say the Trump regime isn't inviting the
current Pakistani prime minister
for any sort of visit. Who's the current
prime minister of Pakistan? I think it's
the Sharif guy, right? The what's his
the brother of Nawas Sharif? Shabbah
Sharif. I as far as I remember that was
the Pakistani prime minister. Last I
checked. He isn't being entertained by
the US. It's Asim Mun, the head of the
military, Pakistani military. So we know
that it's the military that runs
Pakistan. And uh so the US always has
this preference. The US has historically
always preferred to deal with dictators
because dictators can get things done
fast. If you go through the democratic
process and the officially elected
people and all it's a slow long
cumbersome process and who wants to go
through that let's deal with with
dictators and that's why the US has a
track record of installing dictators
wherever they can and Pakistan has been
one of their very significant assets
very reliable assets. So, uh, the US is
dealing, the Trump regime is dealing
with Aim. They're dealing with the
military dictatorship in Pakistan.
They're completely bypassing the
so-called official sovereign dem
democratic allegedly democratically
elected whatever government of Pakistan.
The the the US doesn't believe in
nicities and and you know, keeping up
appearances or whatever. Let's straight
away deal with the dictator. And that's
how it goes. So, the U the the US is
going all in on Pakistan, right? It's
very clear now. Um Trump himself he is
is heavily invested in Pakistan oil and
gas sector, cryptocurrency sector. Um he
seeks to exploit Pakistan's uh rare
earth's mineral sector and so on so so
on so forth so much more. So Trump is
personally invested in Pakistan. The
Trump regime is going all in on Pakistan
and that's what we are seeing. So it's a
complete bypass of the so-called
civilian government in Pakistan and
they're dealing straight with the
military. So that that is how things are
going to be going forward.
Okay, multiple questions about the same
topic. Uh Aush Singh says PM Modi is
visiting China. Putin is coming here as
well to India. What are the chances of
RI Russia India China the sort of
alliance or coalition even if everyone
of us knows that China is a spoiler?
Well, if you've seen my geost strategy
episodes, you will know that China has
been a spoiler when it comes to RIC as
well as bricks. Historically, that's the
role that China has always played and
I've showed that with with all the
evidence you can ask for. Amisha says PM
Modi visiting China for the SEO summit,
Shanghai Cooperation Organization Summit
amid Trump's 50% tariffs on India.
Brazil's president says I won't
humiliate myself. I will not talk to
Trump. I'll talk to Shep Putin Modi. Uh,
can BRICS nations really count for
America? Mcloven says PM Modi is visit v
v v v v v v v v v v v v v v v v v v
visiting China and many leaders
including BRICS leaders are visiting
India. Are we forming a new alliance? We
are witnessing in real time the
reordering of global alliances of the of
the geopolitical world order. Uh are we
moving towards a bipolar world? Are we
are we going to usher in an era of
multipolarity? Well, these days will
tell us. the events the four events of
the next couple of years will tell us
exactly what's going to happen which
direction we're going in so first of all
what are the chances of ra China has
historically been a spoiler but now
China is seems to be at least verbally
extending oliv branches to India they
the Chinese have always preferred to
deal with Russia they would like to see
Russia become a Chinese vasal ideally in
the from the situation and why why not
from their perspective right and they
always well we know the Chinese approach
towards India historically how it's been
right. Uh but now the Chinese are making
nice statements and welcoming Prime
Minister Modi. Um Mr. Mr. Wang Yi is is
arriving in India pretty soon is the
Chinese foreign minister. uh so I think
it looks like we are going towards a
certain direction where India, China,
Russia and other nations BRICS nations
and other nations as well beyond that
may seek to work together
uh in a mutually beneficial way because
everyone's facing the assault from the
US the assault tariffs right uh
essentially tariffs are that you are
excluded from the US market I mean if
you're going to play in the US US market
you're going to be not very competitive
or terribly uncompetitive. That's the
deal with tariffs. Uh so it looks like
there could be the possibility of
something more substantial, something
more robust emerging around bricks or
something like that. So of course
Brazil's president said that I will not
humiliate myself. I will not talk to
Trump. And last I mean recently I myself
said I would not want Mr. Modi to have a
phone conversation with M Mr. Trump
because Trump will try to extract
maximalist concessions from Mr. Modi and
their personal relationship is such that
you know uh certain things which you you
can deny which you can say no to the US
when it comes to u diplomatic
negotiations between diplomats maybe at
the top level you cannot do such things
so I would not want Mr. Modi to speak
with Mr. Trump let Trump ask for a phone
call deny it right. Uh so the question
that Amisha is asking is can the BRICS
nations really counter America? Aisha is
asking what are the chances of rallin
is asking are we forming a new alliance?
Well time will tell us but you know it
makes sense for the nations who are at
the firing line to band together to come
together but uh see bricks is not really
an alliance. It's a coalition of
nations. It's an economic organization
with shared economic interests in a kind
of a common minimum program kind of
thing. Uh but bricks in itself is not
something that can really counter the
US. You need a proper economic alliance
with clearly laid down ground rules and
you know that sort of thing. A proper
framework, proper robust framework,
economic alliance. That's what you need
to really stand up to the US and counter
uh the Trump regime's uh economic
actions of essentially dismantling the
global economic order. Right? So Trump
is a Trump is behaving like the emperors
of old.
If he if he likes you and then he will
give you preferential treatment if you
have somehow offended him he's going to
impose tariffs on you. That sort of
thing. So the old economic order, the
world trade organization, all of that is
being like swept aside. None of that
matters anymore. And Trump will deal
with everybody on a onetoone basis.
Uh so when you have something like that
happening the nations that are in the
firing line especially the nations that
are the big ones that the US is wants to
let's say contain or whatever they need
to get together and have a proper formal
official alliance with with clearly laid
down ground rules and maybe you know a
treaty of some kind. If that happens
then you could say that we are forming a
new alliance. It will happen only if RI
can agree to the to the ground rules and
historically China has been the spoiler.
Now let's see what what role China
plays. Now it looks like this time at
least the the words the words not the
actions the words thus far they kind of
indicate that China may be interested in
something this time. Uh so we'll have we
we will have to see we will have to see.
Can we trust China? Is China potentially
a reliable partner if we form some kind
of alliance, economic alliance, treaty
alliance? Can we rely on them or will
they immediately start bending the rules
or whatever? All of that will have to be
looked into. China's track record isn't
good,
but we'll have to see. So, it looks like
there are moves towards that direction
ra kind of thing, but let's see. It's I
think it's still early days. It'll all
depend on China. It will also depend on
Mr. Modi and Mr. Bhin and how we how the
three leaders uh uh you know go about
things and I think that Mr. Wangi's
visit to India which is which will
happen before Mr. Modi goes to Shang to
to Beijing uh that's going to be
essentially something that sets the tone
for what's going to happen during the
SEO summit and thereafter. So we'll have
a better picture in in a few days. So
let's wait and watch.
Right. More questions about uh yeah
about India US. So Prrenai says what's
the geopolitical and national interest
POV person point of view significance of
Prime Minister Modi openly acknowledging
a heavy price that he's ready to play
ready to pay to protect farmers,
fishermen and dairy interests. Isn't
such a personal cost massive even to
contemplate in today's geopolitical
chess board? Uh Ashish says, "What
personal cost did Prime Minister Modi
hint towards when he declared that he's
he will do whatever it takes to protect
India's sovereignty? Is that a coup that
he's referring to? Regime change,
assassination. What our options going
forward? What are our options going
forward now that we have refused to be
vasalized?" Kind of feeling proud about
it to be honest. Potato praiser says Mr.
Modi in his recent speech said that he
will have to he will even have to bear a
personal cost for not agreeing to open
the farm sector for US companies. Does
this hint that Prime Minister Modi was
possibly threatened to res that somebody
may restart the regime change activities
which were going on during the Biden
regime? Yeah, interesting interesting
set of questions. Prime Minister Modi
recently made a statement very brief
statement. He briefly said that he said
that he's prepared to pay whatever price
price is required to to protect India's
sovereignty and he will have to
potentially possibly bear a sign
significant personal cost for this.
That's what he said. That's what prime
minister said. Mr. Modi said so. So what
does he mean by this? That's the
question that everyone's wondering
about. That's kind of a cryptic
statement. And he did not mention what
kind of price he's talking about. what
kind of personal price we have to bear.
So if I mean is and and Ashish is saying
what does it mean? Is it a coup? Is it a
regime change operation assassination
attempt? What exactly is it? Right?
That's the question. Uh and Ash says he
is feeling proud to be proud that we
have refused to be vosalized. Well, I'm
personally feeling very happy and very
proud that you know uh India has refused
to be vasalized. It's the easy option.
just cave in to the Americans do
whatever they say and everything is
hunky and dory and prime minister gets u
you know special treatment by Mr. Trump
uh you are invited to the US and you
given given very you know red super red
carpet treatment and you treat it like a
personal friend and all that that's the
easy way out but prime minister Modi
said I will not go for that India has to
remain an a sovereign nation we will not
be an American masal we will be nobody's
vasal and we are seeing the consequences
of that all the tariffs all the tantrums
the causing up to Pakistan and all of
that is a consequence of that it
indicates that we have refused to be
vasalized and that that is really
commendable. I'm I'm so proud that we
have a leader who has stood up to the
US. Uh it's not often that we have
leaders who do that in this country the
in the in our history since 1947, right?
We are standing up on our own. Uh so
that's the thing. So what personal cost,
what personal price may the prime
minister have to potentially pay? What
was it referring to? Uh you may see so
and what are the options like you gave
sovereignty um coup regime change
assassination uh you know what during
the 2024 elections there was foreign
interference in the elections in the
electoral process
no question about it there was foreign
interference
there there were huge consistent ongoing
daily attacks uh uh attempts by the
western media to sway the election in a
certain ction
to favor a certain
well political dispens dispensation in
India and it was all anti-Modi anti-BJP
this is external interference in India's
democratic process sovereign democratic
process and the western media we all
know who controls that I mean do I have
to beat around the bush no it's the US
it's the US right so they tried to
influence the course of the election in
2024 for right the farmer protest the
Delhi riots all of that was instigated
by a foreign power exactly when Trump
was visiting India
it was all instigated by a foreign power
the Americans have this policy of
subnational diplomacy of engaging in
subnational diplomacy in India which is
what nothing but essentially trying to
create fissures in India's India's
makeup
it's essentially a long-term plan to
balconize India
What is project Kilan for Christ? That
is an American project. The civil war in
Burma. That also is a proxy war between
essentially the US and China.
So regime change. Yeah, potentially. We
don't know. See, it is it is now being
said by the western media that uh the
relationship between the between the two
countries India and the US it nosedived
after a tense like 20 or 30 minute phone
call between Prime Minister Modi and
President Trump. during operation
synindor.
So I'm not sure what conversation
happened what Mr. Trump may have
threatened. It looks like some threats
were issued. Looks like that. We don't
know what we don't have the readout of
the conversation. It obviously is not
meant for public consumption.
But I'll tell you what, I've said this
before many times. Diplomacy is very
nice in the public domain. The public
diplomacy is always very courteous, very
polite or or kind of frosty at times.
But behind closed doors, diplomacy is
all about bullying, arm twisting,
issuing naked threats. That's what
diplomacy is like behind closed doors.
It's not the nice stuff that you see on
camera. So I don't know what
conversation happened and what threats
may have been issued, but looks like
some threats were issued. Threats to the
country, threats to Mr. Modi potentially
personally. We don't know but that's how
it goes. So if you are the prime
minister of a country you essentially
well you have to be willing to pay any
price that's required for uh in order to
preserve the the security and the
sovereignty of a country and uh yeah so
so that's possibly what Mr. Modi was
talking about. I think when it comes to
threats all options are on the cards. If
you look at the history
of American actions against countries
they don't like, you will say that all
poss potential options are on the table.
So I think that's what Mr. Modi was
referring to.
Okay. Anjuna Malvia says, "What will be
the end of the tariffs drama? If there's
a 500% tariff on India, then what will
be the consequences? Is this the most
vulnerable time for India's sovereignty?
What are the chances of India becoming a
vasal in the coming days? I think let me
answer the last part of the question.
First of all, uh the the way the India
US rel relationship is going now uh
there's no chance of India becoming
overall. India has the the leadership in
India, Prime Minister Modi, he's made a
very clear decision. We will not cave
into the US. The US is essentially the
maximalist demands the US is making, the
Trump regime is making, they're
essentially designed to vasalize India
and India is going to be nobody's vasal.
So that is guaranteed. India has made
the decision now and I think a lot of
people have been caught unawares by
that. I think a lot of people were
expecting India to cave in and to kind
of become a quasi vasal of the US and
that's not happened. It's surprised a
lot of people. I think it has shocked
Donald Trump. I don't think he was
expecting this. So I think the chances
of India becoming a vasal of the US are
zero and that is fantastic. That is
something well I'm so I'm so happy to
see that. Uh is this a most vulnerable
time for India sovereignty? I think it's
not that vulnerable a time for India
sovereignty. U now that the decision to
not become a vasal has been taken, it
means that India is going to remain
sovereign. India will obviously have to
pay a price for remaining sovereign but
India will remain sovereign right now uh
is there a 500 if there's a 500% tariff
on India what will be the consequences
and what's going to be the end state the
end state of the tariff drama so let me
explain what these tariffs are what are
these tariffs what does it mean that
they have imposed x amount of tariffs on
India right now it's 50%. Does it mean
that we are paying 50% of something to
Donald Trump and his regime? It doesn't
mean that. Let me explain what tariffs
are. The US is an entity. It's a nation
which import a lot of stuff from the
whole world. It's the biggest market in
the world, right? Their population 300
and something 30 330 something million.
That's their population. Super rich
country. They consume. They're the
biggest consumer market in the world.
And most of what they consume is
imported from other countries because
the cost of manufacturing is so high in
the US. Ourly wages are so high in the
US. So that's why they they have
everything manufactured in other
countries like China in the past and now
they're looking for alternatives to
China. So so goods are manufactured in
non US countries and those are imported
into the US. So when Trump says that I'm
going to t impose 50% tariffs on Indian
goods let's say what does it mean? It
means that when goods are exported from
India to the US let's say it costs $100
the the price the list price is $100.
So India will export it at $100.
But the company that's importing
it so so let's say there is there is
company A there's company B company A is
an Indian company which is exporting the
goods to company B so company A and
company B have a contract
that company B the importer will pay so
and so price to company A for the goods
that are being imported okay company B
is American company A is Indian so
whatever the contract is will be honored
and company B the American company will
pay as per the contract to the Indian
company whatever the contractual
agreement is. So the Indian company will
make the money will get the money from
the American company. Now when the
American company takes those goods and
sells them in the US market they're
going to have to pay 50% tariffs on
that.
So if something cost a h 100red bucks
$100
used to cost $100. Now they're going to
have to pay they're gonna have to pay a
price of $150. They're going to have to
put it on the market at $150.
This means that the American pop the
American public will have to buy the
goods at $150 instead of $100. So
essentially, it's the American companies
and the American people, the population
that are paying money to Donald Trump
and his administration.
Excuse me. So this makes these Indian
imported these goods that are imported
from India 50% more expensive. But the
Indian company gets the contractually
mandated amount. It's the American
companies and American public that are
paying the American government 50% more.
That's 500. That's 50% tariffs.
Who is paying the brunt? Who is paying
the price? It's the American companies
and American people who are paying the
price to Donald Trump. India is paying
nothing. Of course, that is a So what's
the objective of this tariffs? This the
objective of these tariffs is to
disincentivize
American companies from importing stuff
from India. So maybe then they will say
okay we'll stop importing but it's not
India that's paying the price. It's the
US that's paying the price. It's the
American companies and American people.
What's going to be the end end state of
this? How how does this go? I think
Trump is going to completely reorder the
world. He's going to completely uh
change the way trade is done in the
world. So it's going to end up being
something like the company there's going
to be a bunch of countries which are
which are which are which have to pay
lower tariffs and a bunch of countries
that don't to pay very high tariffs
which means those countries aren't
paying it the American people are paying
it but eventually what it will achieve
is that American companies will stop
will will do less trade eventually with
countries that that are in the higher
tariff bracket. So it means that if if
India is let's say
let's say Donald Trump imposes 500%
tariffs on India it means that India
will essentially in in some time lose
access to the US market which is the
biggest market in the world. So that
will be bad for trade. So it means that
the volume of trade will come down and
the the kind of money that India could
have made from exporting goods and
services to the US that will now drop
significantly. So it's bad for the
Indian economy
and it could have a significant uh
non-trivial impact on India's GDP growth
rate. So the RBI has said that in 2026
we are expected to grow our economy is
expected to grow at around 6.5%.
But if this sort of thing happens if a
500% tar or something like that there
could be a drop of 0.4% roughly. So
instead of growing at 6.5% our GDP will
grow at 6.1% only which is a significant
dent in our GDP growth. So that's that's
the kind of u you know impact it can
have and if uh Trump forces his his
vasal states allied nations EU nations
and whatn not to also implement such
tariffs on India it could hit India's
economy even further and Trump is
capable of forcing other countries into
eventually playing this game.
uh so that's that's de facto sanctions
on uh India or Brazil or whoever is
being targeted in this manner. So
eventually it's going to bipolarize the
world. Yeah. The world not multipolarize
potentially multipolarize also depending
on how things go. So that will obviously
cause significant reactions uh around
the world and uh it could end up
creating an RA coalition or maybe an RA
plus bricks plus kind of coalition and
maybe there could be a formal economic
alliance against the US. Who knows?
We'll have to see. So that's the deal.
Amisha says many interesting
developments are happening. Wangi is
going to visit India this month. Prime
Minister Modi will travel to China at
the end of this month. Yeah, end of
August. Mr. Putin will come to India
later this year. That's correct.
Brazil's president spoke with Prime
Minister Modi on the phone. Looks like
BRICS is getting stronger. The world
order will change. Trump cannot dictate
us on our foreign policy.
I think Trump will chicken out soon.
Taco, what are my thoughts? Taco stands
for Trump always chickens out. That's a
slogan that was coined in the US, not by
us. So yeah, taco means Trump always
chickens out. So what's going to happen?
So clearly the world order will have to
change in response to Trump's actions.
It looks like it may it may happen. It
probably will happen soon. There could
be uh obviously now it looks like the
the interests of India, Russia, China,
Brazil, many other nations they they
work together. There is a significant
convergence of interest. Now the the
convergence of interest is that these
nations all need to stand up to uh
Trump's actions, the the American
actions. So there could be the emergence
of new coalitions, new new alliances. So
it looks like that that could happen.
The world order will definitely change
in response to Trump's actions. Trump
obviously is not going to succeed in his
quest to tell us what our foreign policy
should should look like. Clearly that's
not going to happen. He I think he's
been shocked. He's been caught unawares.
He thought that he would be able to get
away with it and and dictate our foreign
policy to us. Not happened. And I think
he's he's stunned. I think he's furious
as well and he's kind of lost for what
to do now. Should I just keep on ramping
up the tariffs? 50% did not work 75%
100% 500%. Go on, sir. Go on. So that's
the dilemma for Mr. Trump right now. I
think he will potentially increase it
further and see how it how it goes. But
beyond a certain point, the tariffs
don't matter anymore. I think 50% is
already at stage. uh and maybe he's
going to he's going to target India's IT
sector and India's various other
sectors. We'll have to see about that.
Uh so what's going to happen is the
question. Will Trump chickenen out? I
think Trump is going to face a
significant amount of backlash at home
among his own voters because his own
voters are now beginning to see it's
been several months since Trump came to
power. He hasn't achieved any of what he
promised. He said that he would end the
Ukraine war on day one. not happened at
all except that he'll bring inflation
down, prices down. Well, if you impose
tariffs on various imports from various
nations, the prices go up.
So, I think Trump is going to see a
significant erosion of his voter base.
There are some people who worship Trump.
Those will keep on worshiping Trump. But
most people who can think and see what's
see and observe what's happening,
they're going to start losing faith in
Trump.
I think give it a year or so. Trump's
approval ratings will be significantly
lower than what they are. There's going
to be midterm elections in the US. I
think in 2026, next year sometime, I
think there may be significant political
setbacks to him. and the last couple of
years of his Trump of his term. He may
end up being a defect of a virtually
lame duck president.
I think it's this is going to all come
back to bite him,
a sting in the tail. What India has to
do is just to wait this out. Okay,
another three and a half years, no big
deal. We're going to wait it out. So I
think
Trump is going to face a significant
amount of backlash at home when the the
effects the impact of these tariffs
start biting biting the American public
the people who buy stuff that's when
this is going to start biting at the US.
So let's say and they're talking about
ending the H-1B program or changing the
H-1B program. I think if he if he starts
doing that, India should simply declare
that all H1B visas are null and void and
India should should give a 30-day time
period to all Indians with H1B visas to
to return home. I I know it's going to
be terrible for those who are working in
the US because they have hopes and
dreams and aspirations. But this is the
direction in which things are going.
So if India unilaterally ends, not
unilaterally but in response to Trump's
provocations, if India ends the H1B
program and asks all H1B visa holders to
return to India, it's going to cause an
immediate disruption in so many sectors
in the US in the IT sector, in the
technology sector in the in the Fortune
500 companies and so much more. If if
Trump does try to tries to target
India's technology sector, you know,
India's tech sector or India's IT
sector, India could could in response to
that end um all services provided to the
US including BO services, business
process outsourcing, outsourcing. This
would immediately throw the US in a
crisis. All the Fortune 500 companies
rely on India for BO services, IT
services. You end that, it's going to be
a disaster for the US. When it comes to
uh the medical sector, uh India exports
about 40% of America's uh uh what do you
call generic drugs. You end that, it's
going to cause a healthcare crisis in
the US and Trump's approval ratings will
go to zero.
So if Trump wants to play the game, we
can play the game, right? Uh so I think
so these are the like nuclear options
essentially. We don't want to go there.
But if Trump wants to play the game, we
certainly are in a position to position
to play the game. And after a certain
point, tariffs don't matter anymore.
Okay, instead of 50, you make it 75. We
don't care anymore. Make it 500 if you
want. Make it 5,000. We don't care.
After a certain point, it doesn't
matter. So, I think the people in the US
who are who well, they they will see
what's happening. And Trump's approval
ratings will go down and it's going to
it's going to cause a lot of trouble for
Trump. So I think uh Trump may and then
Trump will be will be faced with this
dilemma. Should I bring the tariffs
down? Well then you are tackoing, aren't
you? You're chickening out. So you can
stay stuck with your ego and keep the
tariffs high. But then that will cause
the US public to stop uh believing in
Trump and that will that will be a
disaster for Trump in the midterm
elections. So Trump is going to face a a
a huge crisis of his own making. I'm
seeing this today. Watch out. Let's see
how it goes. I think Trump will end up
ruing his actions.
Okay, a couple of questions about
uranium. Amisha says ministry of
external affairs of India statement
called out the hypocrisy of the US on
importing uranium from Russia. An Indian
reporter asked Trump about this and he
said I don't know anything about it.
Another name of hypocrisy is Trump.
Trump is using the leverage of being a
superpower. They imposed additional 25%
tariffs on India. Mr. Ajit Dualal the
Indian national security adviser visited
Russia. How will India Russia India
Russia counter the US? Now Prren says,
"Isn't this hypocrisy promax? Trump
threatening India over Russian oil while
the while the US itself imports uranium
and fertilizer from Moscow and then
claiming ignorance when asked, does
Washington still think that New Delhi
will bend to such pressure tactics like
before?" Well, Trump has now realized
that India is not going to bend to his
pressure tactics and his pressure
tactics are not going to work at all
beyond a certain amount of tariffs. It
it doesn't matter anymore. So, is it
hypocrisy? Of course, it is hypocrisy.
Europe is importing more more oil and
gas, way more oil and gas from Russia
than India, but he's not going to look
at that. China is importing plenty of
oil and gas from Russia. Trump wouldn't
look at that. The US itself is importing
fertilizers. It's importing uranium higa
fluoride from Russia. They won't look at
that. But India is importing oil and
gas. Terrible evil. Terrible. You're
you're funding your Russ Putin's war
effort. Are you people kidding me?
Anyhow, that's how it is. This is
obviously hypocrisy. But you see, like
I've said in the past, hypocrisy
indicates how powerful you are. Only the
powerful can afford to be hypocritical.
You've got to earn the right to be a
hypocrite. And the US has earned this
right by being by becoming the most
powerful nation in the world. So they
can have double standards. Hypocrisy
means double standards obviously, right?
So yeah, it is hypocrisy and so be it.
It's okay. Let them play these double
games. Let them have double standards.
We're going to point keep on pointing it
out for sure. Yes. And that's what we
did. In the past, the MEA would not have
said this that the US is is is being a
hypocrite. But we have pointed it out
very clearly this time. And Trump, well,
Trump, if you look at his track record,
is shameless.
He has no shame. So, he was asked point
blank by a reporter and he said, "I
didn't know anything about it." All
right. Okay. We all know what what the
deal is. Uh, so look, that's the way of
the world. The US has always been this
sort of a nation, treating one nation
with one set of standards and one set of
rules and other nations with other sets
of rules. It's always been that sort of
thing. They keep on harping about
democracy,
but they prop up dictators all around
the world. They keep on harping about
human rights. They flatten entire
nations. Iraq, Libya. How many people
died during the as a consequence of the
US invasion of Iraq as a consequence of
what they did in Libya? Libya has been
turned into an open air slave market by
the Americans by as a consequence of
American actions.
Doesn't matter. No democracy, human
rights acquired there, right?
So the US has always been this sort of
nation. So it's no surprise that they
are doing this. And I would recommend I
would I would I would invite all of you
to study the US track record
since 1945 until today. What are the
major uh US interventions in Africa?
Major US interventions in other
countries.
What have been the kinds of
interventions?
What have been the consequences of those
interventions? What kind of regime
change operations have they done? Top 20
regime change operations done by the US
and other nations. Check it out. Look it
look it up. That will educate you as to
what sort of track record the US
actually has. So yes, it indeed is is
hypocrisy. They say one thing but do the
do do something which is essentially the
exact opposite of what they claim to
stand for. They do this moral
grandstanding democracy, human rights. I
mean look at their track record. What is
the the US? I mean, look at the nature
of the nation itself.
You know what I call Pakistan, right?
What do I call Pakistan? An artificial
temporary nation.
What is the US?
It's I don't know about temporary, but
artificial absolutely
the nation that's founded on genocide
and slavery and so much more. So that's
how it goes, you know.
Okay. So Abisha says, "How will India
how will India and Russia counter the US
now?" Well, we'll have to see about that
what what can be done. So clearly India
is not going to buy US weapons, US F-35s
or whatever. So I think there's going to
be a strengthening of the India Russia
relationship. Let's not let's not call
it an alliance. It's a privileged
relationship, a strategic relation
relationship. And Mr. Modi recently
tweeted he's going to meet his he's
going he's looking forward to meeting
his friend Mr. Putin, right? And the
Russian readout said that Mr. Putin
apprised Mr. Modi of the recent uh of of
the the communications he had with the
Americans because India and Russia have
a privileged relationship. So we will
share such information. So there is
going to be a significant strengthening
of the India Russia relationship. I
expect this that India will stop
purchasing any kind of American
weaponry. Whatever orders may be on in
the pipeline will be all frozen and
cancelled. I think the Isukoy 57 may
happen, possibly the S500 may happen,
much more may happen. China could jump
into the mix, possibly depending on the
Chinese approach towards all of this. So
I think a lot is possible,
a lot of of synergy is possible between
India and Russia to counter the US.
Amisha says, "China experts are warning
India that we are next in America's
containment containment playbook." Well,
I have been warning that as well for a
long time. Prime Minister Modi should
move India's economy closer to China in
the in the coming three to five years.
America will try to contain India the
way the US did to Japan and is trying to
do to China. Or you can be like the EU
and be a vasal while India has has
chosen not to be a vasal. That's very
clear now, right? We can see that. So
India should move closer to China. So
the question Amisha is asking is should
we move closer to China? Prime Minister
Modi is visiting China this month. How
did the US contain Japanese economic
growth? What are my thoughts? Okay. How
growth? First of all, we have to
understand that Japan is under permanent
US military occupation. So the US can
control each and every every aspect of J
of Japan's economy, of Japan's foreign
policy, Japan's military policy,
everything.
Um the US controls the Bank of Japan for
example. The Bank of Japan can't take a
single significant decision without
consulting and and getting explicit
approval from the American generals who
actually rule Japan. When it comes to
Japan's military policy, everything is
controlled by the US. When it comes to
Japan's foreign policy, everything is
controlled by the US. Japan's
constitution, Japan's education system,
everything is controlled by the US. The
US has more than 130 permanent military
bases on Japanese territory. Complete
control of Japan, which people don't
realize because these things are spoken
about. How did the US contain Japanese
economic growth? In the 1980s, there
were there was this set of accords
called the Plaza Accords between the US
and Japan. Essentially, this was um this
had the effect of of forcing the the
Bank of Japan to change interest rates
and make some I'll not go into the
details but make some modifications
in the Japanese economy which caused a
slow steady almost imperceptible
gradual very slow decline in the
Japanese economy, Japanese consumption
patterns and so much more. And the
consequence of that is is the is that
Japan is now almost a middle- inome
country. It was one of the highest
income countries in the world in the
1980s. It's now almost a middle inome
country. The GDP per capita has dropped
that much significantly. It's almost
half I would say of what is what it used
to be. They destroyed Japan's economy,
right? But can they do that to India?
They don't control the Indian
government, the Indian economy, nothing.
We are a sovereign nation unlike
unfortunately sadly Japan. Japan is not
sovereign. So sad. Anyway, uh so that's
how the Americans
affected this slow gradual almost
imperceptible implosion of Japan's
economy. Now China experts are warning
India that we are next in the America's
containment playbook. While well when
you look at the election interference in
2024 general elections, well that's
containment. That's an attempt to
contain India. when it comes to uh the
American attempts to play these uh
subnational diplomacy games, that's an
attempt to create problems and trouble
in India. When it comes to the Delhi
riots, the uh the whatever happened in
Delhi, all all that stuff uh during Mr.
Trump's visit in 2019 or where whenever
it was, well, that's containment. When
you have project K, Cookie Land for
Christ,
H, that is containment. when it comes to
the American support to Pakistan now
very open very blatant very out very
outright support to Pakistan now that's
containment
all of this is containment so the
Chinese what they're telling us is
something we have known for quite some
time it's not something new the
government I mean the public Indian
public may not see it the government of
India knows exactly what's happening
right it's the same government since
2014 the same set of people essentially
the same there's continuity So the
government of India, Prime Minister
Modi, they know exactly what the
Americans are doing. This is called
containment. Sure.
So the Chinese are not telling us
something new. But the fact that they
are saying this is interesting because
China historically has been okay with
that. They themselves have tried to
contain India. Even the Chinese by
supporting Pakistan like they've done so
much. The the Chinese also have done
have played the same game. But now they
are warning that the Americans are
playing this containment game. Uh and
they're recommending that Prime Minister
Modi should move India's economy closer
to China. Well, we'll have to see about
that. Look, obviously there's going to
be some kind of decoupling between India
and the US economically like based on
what Trump is doing, what the Trump
regime is doing. Um, of course, it all
depends on what happens over the next
year, year and a half. There's going to
be a significant backlash in the US to
Trump's actions because it's going to
hurt the American public. it's going to
hurt them financially, economically and
they're already struggling bas because
of the Biden regime's policies which
cause so much inflation and so much
more. Uh so what should India do? See
clearly India is not going to be a
vasal. That decision has been taken now.
So India is going to have to pay the
price for that of that uh and we are
paying the price of that. we going to
have to essentially there could be some
more pain coming our way potentially in
the in the coming weeks and months. So
America is trying to contain India.
Sure. So so what should India do? Can we
move our our economy closer to China in
the coming months in the coming 3 to 5
years? So the question is what does it
mean that we should move our economy
closer to China? What does it mean?
Should we open our up up our market and
make it a dumping ground for Chinese
cheap products? That doesn't work. that
will cause an even more tra trade
imbalance between India and China. It
has to be something that's mutually
beneficial. It cannot be beneficial to
one country and disastrous for the other
other country. If you open up our
economy to Chinese goods, cheap Chinese
goods, it'll destroy our manufacturing
sector because then the Chinese goods
will be so cheap and so easily available
that Indians will only buy that. The
Indian people don't understand the
difference, right? The cheapest product
is what you'll buy as long as it's
reasonably
Okay quality. So what does it mean that
we should move our economy closer to
China? In what way?
That's something they will have to well
elaborate about. So if the Chinese are
willing
to have some kind of a mutually
beneficial relationship, economic
relationship, then we can explore that.
We then China is a dictatorship. So we
can we don't have to go and talk to
Chinese companies and all. We just have
to talk talk to the government and we
can hammer out some kind of agreement
and we then we can implement that. It
will it will have to be mutually
beneficial. It cannot it cannot be
something that will destroy India's
manufacturing sector. It will have to be
something that is mutually beneficial.
Um I'm sure the sky is the limit when it
comes to cooperation potentially between
India and China. So much can be done if
the two nations are genuinely willing to
work together. It depends. So that will
only depend that will depend entirely
essentially on the Chinese government.
So that is something we have to see. It
would be good. It would be beneficial
for both countries if if that sort of
thing happens. But will it happen? It'll
all depend on the Chinese government's
approach.
Geopolitical Dubai says how significant
is Prime Minister Modi's upcoming visit
to China? Will it infuriate Shri Trump
more?
Uh Mr. Modi is is is slated to visit
China the end of this month? I think
August 31st and September the 1st, the
Shanghai Cooperation Organizations
Summit probably in Beijing if I'm not
mistaken or wherever it is in China. Um,
so Mr. Modi will be there. Mr. Xiinping
obviously is a host and Mr. Putin will
be there, right? It's a pretty
significant meeting. It's the first time
in God knows how many years Mr. Modi is
going to China. Probably the first time
in about 7 years. I think the last time
Mr. Modi was in China was probably
around 2018.
So it's after 7 years that he's visiting
China. And it's it's significant because
because Mr. Putin is also going to be
there and the various other leaders of
various other SEO nations it's going to
be a pretty significant event. Now just
because the three leaders are there the
big three Mr. Putin, Mr. Modi and Mr.
Shei that itself makes it a significant
event. Uh there's the potential that
there could be bilateral talks between
Mr. Modi official proper bilateral talks
between Mr. Modi and Mr. Xi. That's in
the offing potentially. Mr. Wangi is
visiting India this month. China's
foreign minister and probably he's going
to have discussions detailed discussions
with his in counterpart Mr. Dr.
Jashankar and the two the two foreign
ministers will then chalk out the
approach that we need to take and
whether a bilateral uh meeting will
happen between Mr. Modi and Mr. If that
happens, it's it's going to be more
significant.
And at the end of the day, what will
really matter is what is the outcome of
the summit is there? If there is a ra
kind of outcome,
then that will be huge event globally.
It'll be it'll have huge uh consequences
globally. The whole world will sit up
and watch and see and and wonder what
happens next. So if there is some kind
of
forward direction that emerges from the
sh from the from this summit between the
leaders of the three nations and and
something significant goes ahead that
will obviously be set of alarm bells in
the US because it's not just India it's
India Russia China
and that will definitely infuriate Shri
Trump but uh well he if if that happens
Mr. Trump only Shri Trump only has
himself to blame for that right I mean
the India US relationship was great it
was going great but Mr. Trump comes and
dynamites it. So then what does he
expect? Shri Trump G.
Funny guy says should India exit the
quad? Well options all options are on
the table. See the the the quad
is a well if you look at the history of
the quad it is something that was
probably thought up by Shri Shinszu Abbe
of of Japan. It was probably his
brainchild. the late Shri Shinszu AB who
was assassinated by god knows who. So u
the quad is this quadrilateral
kind of alliance or or or coalition of
nations. It's India, it's Japan, it's
Australia Australia and it's the US and
uh it's not officially a military
alliance or any such thing but the
Chinese see it as a anti-China alliance
as an alliance whose sole objective is
to contain China. That's how the Chinese
see it.
Now um a lot could change in the coming
days. Maybe the India China relation
equation may change. Maybe India, China,
Russia, the trilateral equation may
change. A lot could happen. And if
things go in such a direction that we no
longer perceive a threat or a
significant threat from China, if things
go in that direction, then India's
participation in the Quad is moot. We
don't need that. And of course the US
uh the US approach the US attitude will
also matter right if the US is is uh is
prioritizing its interests with Pakistan
over its interests over its relations
with India if the US are supporting
Pakistan and strengthening Pakistan and
investing in Pakistan well then what's
the point of India being in a in a
quadlike uh you know coalition with the
with the US which is openly anti-India.
Yeah, you support Pakistan, you are
automatically anti-India, aren't you?
Right? So, all the options I would say
are on the table right now.
It will depend on how things go with
China. So, Mr. Wangi comes to India this
month. We will have some kind of
indication that Mr. Modi goes to China
at the end of the month and how things
go there, we will have to see. So it
will to a large extent depend on the
Chinese approach and the Chinese uh and
and and how things go between India and
China. India and Russia everything is
good but the quad hasn't anything
doesn't really have much to do with
Russia. It's more to do with China. So
the relationship between India and India
and the US is not good anymore. It's
it's that's very clear. The US is openly
supporting Pakistan. I mean that that
should tell you everything you need to
know. So all that matters, all that is
left now is to see how things go between
India and China. If the Chinese are
willing to start a new chapter,
then you know it may be
possible that India may exit the quad.
That would be a significant actually you
know gamecher because that would that
would seal the rift between India and
the US.
that that would be something that India
can't walk back from. Once you're out,
you're out. After a few months, you
can't say, "Okay, I would like to be
back in." It doesn't work like that. So,
it's a very final decision, this exit
from the quad, potential exit from the
quad. But it will all depend on these
factors like I mentioned. And I think
exiting the quad is also something
that's going to be seriously on the
table.
Amisha says, "I think Trump has provided
India a once in a generation opportunity
to take the next big leap on reforms.
The crisis must be fully utilized. But
in India, we have all these freebies
schemes largely bahhana, yojana and
whatnot and mandrega and whatever it is,
you know, freebies schemes. Politicians
and some lazy incompetent people are
feasting on taxpayers money." Allegedly
true. Yeah. Allegedly. Very true.
Allegedly. So how will we counter Trump
China amid this situation which is this
is so frustrating.
So you are absolutely right that uh we
have a once in a generation opportunity
to to enact significant reforms in the
country.
See one of the major pieces in the
jigsaw puzzle when it comes to India's
GDP growth rate and India's uh
aspiration to become a 20 trillion $30
trillion economy one of the major
components of that was India becoming a
manufacturing power major manufacturing
power and obviously the country that
would absorb the manufacturing would be
the US that was the well that's how it
was seen because the US is the world's
biggest richest market the biggest
consumer economy in the world and if you
are manufacturing If you if you're a
major manufacturing power, you want to
export to the US. That's where you make
the most money. That's how China became
a major power, economic power, right? So
now it looks like it's not going to be
on the cards, at least as long as Trump
is in power, right? As long as the Trump
regime is in power, this is not going to
be the case. So if we become a
manufacturing power, where do we export
to? That's the question. The question
is, does China need imports?
I don't think China needs to import
anything because they are the biggest
manufacturing power in the world. So
then the question is where do we export
to if we become a manufacturing power do
we export to the EU the European Union?
Well that's a significantly decent sized
market but well they are controlled by
the US. The EU is a vasal of the US all
these nations and then the US can choke
that off also. So yeah so then the
question is then if we become a
manufacturing power who consumes who
consumes what we manufacture? We'll have
to become a manufacturing power that has
domestic consumption. Then that's also
an option. Domestic consumption, we
manufacture for ourselves.
That can be also something that boosts
the economy. But for all of these things
to happen, you need reforms in India.
There's still too much red tape. There's
still allegedly too much too much
allegedly corruption.
There's too much
inertia. There's too there's too many
problems in the country. A lot needs to
change. All of these government schemes
that are freebie schemes, those need to
end. That's when we can free up our
economy. I mean I mean the excheer to
invest money in R&D, invest money in
defense, invest money in other things.
So yeah, this is a great opportunity to
enact big bang reforms, huge reforms
that will have uh positive consequences
for decades. This is indeed that sort of
opportunity. we need to if you want
India to become let's say a
consumption-driven economy well then
people need to have more money to
consume right but if you if you have all
this ownorous taxes and whatn not all
kinds of taxes people have to pay if you
are an income tax player then payer then
you're paying income tax then you're
being taxed for everything else also GST
no matter what you purchase in India
there's GST on it so how can you say
that Indian Indians don't pay tax
everybody pays tax so this all of this
needs to be looked into we We need huge
reforms. We need to simplify the
taxation regime. We need to make doing
business in India way easier than it is
right now. We have to essentially
unshackle India's economic growth
engine. So yeah, this is indeed that
sort of opportunity. Now that you know
things are bad with the US, we have to
look at other avenues for economic
growth.
So it's it's that sort of time where we
can potentially make huge uh changes in
the way things are done reforms.
So the problem is this and that's where
Amisha is frustrated and rightly so that
if Mr. Modi cuts down on those freebie
schemes.
Well, very soon the BJ BJP will start
losing elections because Indians are
addicted to freebies,
right? All of this will lead deep
changes in India. The thought process of
Indians has to change.
Indians need to be taught that freebies
are are poison.
They actually do more harm than good. It
makes you completely unproductive.
It doesn't allow you to to explore your
full potential because you're satisfied
because the government is giving you
free stuff at the expense of everybody
else.
But to do that, you have to change
things deeply like the education system
and all that. So we'll not go there. So
I think so that's the problem. That's
the issue that Mr. Modi faces. If he
makes these big changes, if he ends
these freebies, then he's going to lose
the next election. Indians will vote him
out of power. They'll vote the BJP out
of power. So yeah, it's that sort of
situation catch 22. But something needs
to change. So let's see how it goes. But
yeah, we do need reforms, huge reforms,
major reforms.
Animesh Paul says, since India currently
lacks technological sovereignty, how
would we cope if the US cuts off access
to platforms like Google, Meta,
WhatsApp, YouTube, and X? Do we have any
real alternatives? Isn't now the time to
invest in in and develop our own
technology. How should we plan and
execute such an initiative to be ready
for the challenging times ahead
challenging times ahead? That's a
question by anime and there's another
question which is along the same lines.
This is by CJ Joy Joe.
I'm a long-term follow follower of you.
Thank you so much sir. Thank you. Uh why
is India not acting like China and
Russia? We know that our internet and
necessary functionalities are
functioning in ter in the on the terms
of the west or from from the support of
the west from the west especially in the
US. The most important factor is the
operating system. The Chinese have their
own operating system harmony OS which is
not based on Linux. It's an entirely
original OS. Yeah, Russia has their own
internal autonomous functioning internet
even if the west cuts them off entirely.
India doesn't have it. China has a great
firewall of China. Isn't this a leverage
to the west which can be used against
us? We aren't even supporting
alternatives. Even our government
communications are happening via
WhatsApp. What if they decide to pull
all the Microsoft tactics like you know
deny Microsoft services and so on? Will
the government even the basic punchad
functionalities get doomed? Will we have
to go back to using telegrams?
I say this to many at least don't try to
purchase everything from a single
monopolistic giant like meta. at least
try to shift our main messenger app
which is WhatsApp to Telegram. Keep it
in mind that Meta is not taking proper
action against anti-India contents but
they swiftly act and impose strong
action against other silly matters.
Rectifying these issues or filling the
gap in our true autonomy will give us a
lot of geopolitical advantages. What do
I think? Please include it in your live
session. I am including it. It's very
important. What you're saying is very
very true. It's very important. I think
India is about 2 to three years before
this sort of thing to happen. maybe even
sooner than that.
India needs to have its own operating
systems. India needs to be able to
manufacture manufacture its own PCs and
laptops. India needs to have its own
apps. India needs to have its own social
media platforms. Social media is
important. I think it's a vital
necessity today in today's world. All
Indians are connected today. We
understand Indians from all parts of
India because of social media. If social
media services are denied to India then
Indians will once again be completely
isolated and apart from each other right
u so we need to have our own operating
systems we need to have our own
manufactured our own internally
manufactured PCs laptops whatever phones
we need to have uh our own Indian
indigenous mobile operating system our
own uh laptop operating systems which
are independent of anything from the
west yes we need to have our own
internet uh even if the rest of the
world is cut off. We need to be able to
communicate with each with with each
other. We need to have our own social
media platform. At least one we don't
need meta and Twitter and this and that
and everything. At least one social
media platform has to be there. Now the
question is who does this? Who does
this? Does the government is the
government supposed to create this or
are Indian private companies supposed to
do this? idea. I mean if you look at the
US all these all these services that we
use whether it is Meta or Google,
WhatsApp whatever these are all private
companies that have created these
product products. So ideally you would
want Indian private companies to to
create world-class products. We have all
these IT IT services companies that
offer IT services to the west. Why can't
they come up with this? They we have the
best IT brains in the world. Millions
tens hundreds of millions of these. So
why it's obviously going to be easy for
an Indian company if it decides to to
create services, platforms, apps,
whatever operating systems, it'll be
easy. But they simply don't care. They
don't want to do it because they want to
keep on playing the game of labor
arbitrage with the west, you know, and
that's how they have made money thus
far. But they're going to be hit very
badly now. First of all, the AI uh the
advent of AI is going to hit everything,
all the IT services in India. And
secondly, Trump may take some action
against Indian IT companies.
um an Indian Indian IT export services
exports to the US it may happen pretty
soon so I think it's it's a question of
time maybe two three years possibly
before maybe even sooner before this
sort of scenario happens
uh so if the Indian IT companies aren't
willing to do this maybe the Indian
government needs to take action what did
uh Animesh say once again same thing
technological sovereignty yes if what
what happens if the US cuts off access
to these platforms well we are left a
drift right that's what happens. So
obviously I completely agree with what
with what Cjoy Jo is saying. This needs
to be taken up on a war footing. India
needs to have its own operating systems.
Uh Indian government servants need to
immediately stop using Gmail,
using WhatsApp. We need to have our own
secure communications apps, our own
email services. Everything should be
indig indigenized because the world may
very soon decouple and all these
services that you're taking for granted
may disappear. So very important points
are being raised over here and I
completely agree with these points.
Sporty says China has done reverse
engineering in many sectors especially
in aviation and aerospace. What's
stopping India from doing the same? I
have absolutely no idea what is stopping
India from doing the same. Let me show
you something. I was looking because I
saw this question. When I selected this,
I was looking up, do we have a list of
things the Chinese have reverse
engineered? And let me show you what the
Chinese, this is just a small aspect of
what the Chinese have reverse
engineered. So I found this. This is an
article from 2014. Okay, let's see the
kind of things the Chinese have reverse
engineered. The Chinese Russian manned
Soyuse space capsule which is now called
the Shenzu manned spacecraft. The
Chinese reverse engineered a Russian
design. The chi the Russian Sukoy 27 is
now the Shenyang J11B.
Shenyang J11B. The chi the Russian MIG
17 Shenyang J5. Mig 19 Shenyang J6. Mig
19 L. Mig 21 L. Sukoy 33 Shenyang J15
Flying Shark. Mig 21 is the J17 JF7
Thunder Chindus F7.
uh MIG 23 MS, Nanch Q6, Russian Antonov
A&12, the Shangi Y8, the Yakovv
130, the Hongdu L15 Falcon,
the F-35 Lightning, F22 Raptor, the
Shenyang J31 stealth fighter, the MQ1
Predator, the Changdoop Theodactyl. They
have reverse engineered everything you
can imagine. piston engines, jet
engines, uh, Snikma by high high bypass
turbo fan. That's the Shenyang WS10
which failed. Then you have the Shenyang
WS10A which is based on the Russian
Saturn turopan Saturn AL31F turboan
engine. Um, the American Humvey is the
Dongfang uh whatever brave soldier
thing.
Strila man pads Honging HN5 ballistic
missile defense system S300 the Chinese
have the Hong Ki HQ9
Israeli spike missiles they've made
their own copy of that the Russian KH31
cruise missile skimming sea skimming
cruise missile the Ying I mean this goes
on and on they they've reverse
engineered anti-hship missiles
lightweight torpedoes battle tanks
rocket launchers pistols
Everything you can imagine the Chinese
have reverse engineered that. And does
this mean that the Chinese are stupid or
bad? No. I think this is what you have
to do. Like I always say, buy, beg,
borrow, steal technology. No matter what
it takes, acquire the technology that is
necessary for you to have in line with
your national interest. The Chinese have
done this. They've been doing this for
decades. Since the middle of the 20th
century, they've been doing this.
Whatever they purchase from another
country, they will re they will
dismantle and reverse engineer the whole
thing. The Russians know it very well.
So many Russian products have been
reverse engineered by the Chinese. Yeah.
But India won't do that. No, we won't do
that. Why is it so? Multiple reasons I
would say. One is because of alleged
corruption. It is said that allegedly
Indian uh
officials received allegedly lots of
kickbacks for purchasing products from
the west in other countries. So if
you're allegedly receiving kickbacks for
these sales, why would you want to
develop this at home?
That's one thing. Secondly, I just don't
know when you have so much bureaucracy
and and and all of that in your
organizations, there is no incentive to
do something out of the box. You're
actually disincentivized
to to be in know from being innovative
from doing such things. I think it's a
lack of leadership. It's a lack of
vision. It's it's it's alleged
corruption, alleged god knows what else.
All of this has has meant that we have
never bothered to reverse engineer
anything anything. I would say even
today if you were to build the MIG 21,
the MIG 21 is being retired now, right?
Because it's such an old aircraft. The
MIG 21's engine, if you were to
manufacture that engine at home in India
with brand new components, which means
you're manufacturing brand new engines.
And if you are manufacturing the entire
MiG 21 at home with brand new
components, then it's going to be a
spanking new aircraft. The reason why
the Mig21s have had so many crashes,
it's because these are aircraft that
were first purchased in the 1960s and
'7s. They're 50 60 year old airframes.
But if you if you were to manufacture
the same airframes today in 2025, brand
new airframes, I promise you, the big 21
can still take out all of Pakistan's
F-16s.
But we never bothered to do those
things. We got the blueprints. We got
everything for the Mig2. We never
manufactured them at home. We simply
assembled them at home.
A lack of leadership, a lack of vision,
a lack of I don't know what to say.
So it's it's a I mean it's a huge self
goal by India. Never having re reverse
engineered anything. We should have
reverse engineered everything. We bought
the Mirage, the Sukoys. Sure, we can pay
Russia for for it. But we should have
reverse engineered everything,
the tanks, what not. We should reverse
engineer those those
general atomics drones we have bought
from the US. We should reverse engineer
the the the the Rafal. We should reverse
engineer everything. I don't know what's
stopping us from doing this. Every
country does it. I don't know why they
have not done it. I think hopefully now
things will change. But yeah, it's a
good point you're raising here.
Pernai says with India pausing a $3.6
billion Boeing deal after Trump's
repeated tariff threats are US India
ties at one of their lowest points in
decades and what does this mean for
future defense and trade cooperation?
We have paused frozen whatever you want
to call it this uh deal uh I think six
or eight aircraft we're supposed to buy
from the US. These are not civilian
aircraft. These are the Boeing Poseidon
aircraft. Let me show you what that
means. Um, let's go to Google.
Uh, Boeing
Poseidon.
This is the aircraft, the Boeing P8
Um, how many of these do we have? We
have 12 of these. And there's more in
the pipeline potentially, but we have
chosen now to freeze that order. So
these are uh maritime patrol and
reconnaissance aircraft which
essentially are used to to detect
submarines and potentially even
neutralize submarines, enemy submarines
in in in maritime regions of your
interest. So that's the aircraft that uh
that Boeing deal it's it's manufactured
by the by the Boeing company. So that's
the deal that's been frozen or or paused
or whatever you want to call it.
So that's happened. Now does it mean
that India US ties are at one of their
lowest points in decades? Yes, it means
that absolutely India US relations are
at their lowest point in many decades.
Uh and what does it mean for the future
for future defense and trade
cooperation? Uh trade we discussed
defense it's over. India is going to buy
nothing from the US. Now
whatever strategic trust had been built
up between the between the US and India
between India and the US over the past
few decades it's gone. It's evaporated.
The moment the US openly sides with
Pakistan it's over. There's zero
strategic trust automatically. Whatever
trust they had built up the Americans
and India is gone. It's over. There's
going to be no future defense and trade
cooperation. Trump was dreaming of
selling F-35s to India. Keep dreaming,
bro. Not going to happen. So, it's over.
It's not going to happen. I think
whatever else we supposed to buy, the
Striker or Python or whatever uh
anti-tank systems and whatever else was
there, it's over. Not going to happen.
Um what happens with the jet engines?
We'll have to see. We'll have to see
about that because we we have this deal
with the Americans of purchasing jet
engines for our theas fighter planes. I
think that could could be impacted.
We'll have to see. So, what happens
then? Do we purchase engines from the
French? Will they fit into the airframe?
The Russian uh Saturn engines
are are probably too large for the
Tajjas. So, what happens now? There's
going to be a lot of pain that India is
going to have to swallow. And if if the
Americans are making us swallow all this
pain, do you think there's going to be
any trust left from our side towards
them? No. It's over. So there's going to
be no more defense cooperation. Trade we
already discussed.
Geopolitical Dubet says, "How can both
Russia and America let an American ally
which is the Philippines have the Brahos
missile? Is it only to contain China in
the South China Sea?" And Brianka Seeker
Biswar says during his recent India
visit the Filipino president uh sought
more Indian defense technology including
the including more Brahos missiles as
the Philippines is is a US vasal
unfortunately it is with permanent US
military bases could this not fall into
American hands and doesn't China fear
the same with the arms that it supplies
to US aligned Pakistan
so the Philippines already has a couple
of regiments at least I believe of the
Brahos Messiah. Let's let's quickly
Google it. How many Brahos regiments
does the Philippines have? One second.
Let me put that on the screen. Let's
Google it.
How
many Brahmos
regiments
does
Philippines have?
They purchase. Okay. Three missile
batteries. Okay. regiments. Okay. BRAMOS
batteries
batteries does the Philippines have
um
nine additional. So they have a couple
of couple of batteries like was being
mentioned here. They have purchased
three and they have received two at
least as far as I remember and they want
more apparently. Right. Yeah. So the
Philippines already has Brahmos missiles
and there could be more. They want more.
So the question is the Philippines is a
US ally US vasal unfortunately. So if we
are selling Brahma missiles to the
Philippines, won't the Americans get
their hands on the Brahma missile and
and and and get access to all the
technological secrets?
Well, you see, whenever a nation, like
I've said this before, whenever a nation
exports
mater exports weapons, let's say, to
some other country, you sell them the
export version, which is not the full
version that you use. So, it's going to
have some some stuff left out. All the
all the critical technologies won't be
there. It'll still be a pretty good
weapon system. So, for example, if the
Americans are selling us F-35s
potentially, like they were hoping, they
would have sold us a knockdown export
variant, which would be about one/ird as
effective as the American version.
That's how it goes. And that too with
all those back doors and kill switches
and whatnot.
And when the Chinese export whatever
they export to Pakistan, that's also the
export version. That's not the full
version. It's not fully capable. It has
things left out and whatnot. So I expect
that the BRAMOS that's been sold to
whoever is going to be the export
version. See the BRAMOS missile system
is a joint India Russia production,
right? It's been developed jointly by
the two countries. And as such
whenever the bramos corporation sells
bramos missiles to any country it first
takes has to take approval from the
governments of both India and Russia and
it's only when both nations agree that a
sale happens. So if a sale has happened
to the Philippines it means that India
and Russia are both okay with it. So
they've done their threat and risk
assessment and they have said it's fine.
That's how it goes. So that's why it's
okay to to sell it to the Philippines.
And obviously the Philippines are
concerned about China. China is a big
threat to them and that's why and even
Russia was okay with this. You see
that's a game that are played in
geopolitics geopolitical games.
Right. Amisha says Putin will meet Trump
in Alaska on the 15th of August. Putin
is saying he will stop the war in
exchange for eastern Ukraine. Do you
think Trump will agree to it? Is India's
the the tariffs on India are they going
to be discussed? This is a major summit.
I think this will change geopolitics.
Your thoughts on this summit? Will be
will it be successful or or will it
fail? And Pra says Trump put in to meet
on 15 August in Alaska halfway between
Moscow and Washington. Beyond optics,
what geopolitical calculus does this
location and timing signal in the
current US Russia dynamic?
So it looks like it's going to be Alaska
somewhere in Alaska. Now if you look,
okay, we haven't opened the map today.
So let's go to the map and let's take a
look at Alaska.
Let's take a look at Alaska. Let's uh
yeah, here we have it. Okay, let's go
eastwards.
So, if you see if you look at Russia's
far east, we're looking in the far east
of Russia. This is Kamchatka over here.
And then you have the bearing see the
illusion state and east
further east of Russia, you have Alaska.
And Alaska used to be a Russian
territory
long ago.
It used to be owned by Russia and Russia
sold it to the United States. So this is
a territory that is now owned by the US,
but it's a formerly Russian territory.
So that's the well deeper historical
significance of Alaska. It is it is
something that has well it has both
Russian and American that sort of
connection, right? So maybe that's the
reason why Trump chose Alaska. Maybe
because this was a former Russian
territory and now it's American. Maybe
there is some significance to that.
Beyond that there is no other
geopolitical significance. It's it's
historical significance.
Um so yeah there is no other
geopolitical calculus to using this
location timing. I don't know maybe it's
a mutually acceptable date August 15th.
I don't think it has anything to do with
India because as we know in August 15th
is India's independence day. the day we
got independent
status from the British.
Uh so now the question Amisha is asking
is Putin is saying that he will stop the
war in exchange for eastern Ukraine. Do
you think Trump will agree to it? Well,
Trump may obviously ask for some
concessions and if those concessions uh
are if if Mr. Putin is willing to give
those concessions the war may end. So as
you can see that as you can see Mr.
Zalinski has nothing to do with with the
summit. And let's say that the US and
Russia agree to something that we end
the war if this happens. But what if Mr.
Zalinsky says no, I will not agree to
it. Then what if the EU nations support
Zalinski and disobey Mr. Trump? So
there's plenty of complications that
could happen. There are plenty of
potential complications to even if
there's an agreement that is reached
between Mr. Mr. Putin and Mr. Trump.
Will India's tariffs be discussed in
this? Most likely not. This is about
Ukraine. This entire meeting, the
entire, you know, agenda is going to be
Ukraine, ending the Ukraine war. Trump
is desperate to end the Ukraine war. He
wants a Nobel Peace Prize no matter what
happens.
And if he successfully ends the Ukraine
war, well, then he he will say that now
I'm going to go to Stockholm and get the
prize for myself. Even if the Nobel
committee doesn't give it, I'm going to
go to Stockholm. I'll take it. So Trump
is desperate to end the Ukraine war. He
has been saying that he has ended so
many wars and whatnot allegedly, right?
Uh and Putin will have his demands. So
once again, let's take a look at the
map. How much of Ukraine does Russia
currently uh control is the question. So
if we look at Ukraine,
Ukraine is over here north of the Black
Sea. So roughly a quarter between a
fifth and a fourth of Ukraine is
currently controlled by Russia. And it
is possible that just before the summit
happens, Russia may potentially take
more territory just to have a stronger
negotiating position. That is certainly
possible.
So what exactly does eastern Ukraine
mean? That also we will have to see.
What does Mr. Putin mean by eastern
Ukraine? So as of now right now that's
the situation in Ukraine. Russia
controls about between a fifth and a
fourth of the territory of Ukraine. Um
oh where are we? Yeah yeah this this
over here. So will the Americans be okay
with with Russia keeping the that
territory or maybe more? Mr. Putin may
even say that you know what we don't
control this much portion of it but we
want this and this and this also and
Zelinsky will have to give it to us even
though we currently don't control it
that also is something that Mr. Putin
may ask for why not if you want to
negotiate you you've got to negotiate
hard uh so what do I think will the two
leaders Mr. Trump and Mr. Bhin be able
to negotiate an end to the Ukraine war
on August 15th. This this meeting in
Alaska. We will have to see. We'll have
to see. I think it's less than 50/50. I
think it's very difficult to
to to bring bring about a negotiated
settlement of the war without involving
Mr. Zalinsky because Mr. Zilinski has
been pushed on a ped pedestal and made
transformed into this very big figure.
So even if Mr. Trump and Mr. Putin
agree, Mr. Zelinsky may have refused to
cooperate. Then once again Trump may say
I will stop sending aid to Ukraine then
the EU may also say that you know what
we will keep on aiding Ukraine. There's
so much complications that could happen.
Uh so I think right now it's difficult
to see this war ending that soon. you
may need multiple meetings and multiple
sets of negotiations, maybe an ongoing
negotiation for a few months perhaps at
least a few weeks for and that that
would potentially involve more than just
just the US and Russia for this war to
end. So I think this could be the
beginning of that sort of process.
Now once again about about the location,
why not a location in Russia?
Why is this meeting happening in in
Alaska? Why not in Kamchatka in Russia?
Has Mr. Trump refused to visit Russia. I
mean, what what is the deal behind that?
And why has Mr. Putin apparently agreed
to Alaska? Uh, we will have to see why
that is the case. Does Mr. Yeah. Well,
obviously, if Mr. Putin visits the US on
a state visit, on an official visit, the
Americans can't do anything to him.
Yeah, but it's interesting. Interesting.
Definitely.
Okay. General says, "Is oil and gas the
only thing stopping us from becoming an
utarchy raw material wise?" So what's an
utarch? An otarchy is a nation or a
kingdom or an empire that is completely
100% entirely self-sufficient
in resources. Oil, gas, coal, iron,
steel, fertilizer, agriculture, food,
fisheries, everything, chemicals,
industry, everything. You're completely
self-sufficient. So mainly it's about
raw materials. Obviously, mainly that's
an archive. So I think the only thing
that's stopping us from being in a
Turkey is oil and gas. Our our reliance,
our dependence on importing oil and gas.
We don't have sufficient resources that
we know of, reserves that we know of of
oil and gas. And that's why we have to
import I think 60% or more of our oil
and gas from other countries. And that's
one of the major Achilles heels of India
that we are dependent on other nations
for this critical thing energy. You see
if you see my geopolitics course those
of you who have who are me who have
purchased it they will know that no
geopolitical activity happens without
the expenditure of energy.
No human activity is pos possible
without the expenditure of energy. Every
single thing every human activity
involves spending energy burning energy.
Right? So that's the most critical thing
and uh yeah so India imports about 60%
or more of its oil and gas from other
countries and that is I think the only
thing that's preventing India from being
an utarchy when it comes to other things
like
like like like for example agriculture
when it comes to um what about metals
iron I think India probably India is
such a huge place India probably has
most of everything it needs apart from
oil and So most likely if if this thing
is fulfilled, if India deserves
discovers large resources of oil and gas
somewhere sufficient to um take care of
India's needs, then India is more or
less anarchy by that once that happens.
So I think yeah that's the only missing
piece of the puzzle for India to become
an otterarchy.
Okay, next question.
Okay, this is by Nayan Joti Bora. The
question is,
what was the reason the Chinese army
withdrew from Indian territories despite
winning the 1962 war? They came up to
Assam but somehow withdrew their troops,
the 1962 war, right? So the Chinese army
did come up to Assam, parts of Assam.
And the great magnificent Shri Nehuji
the prime minister of India at that time
he had uh he had given an address on the
on all India radio saying that my heart
goes out for the to the people of Assam
or something. Essentially
some people some historians have taken
it to signify that he was willing to
give up Assam and other people dispute
that claim.
Right? My heart goes out to the people
of Assam. So like you know I can't do a
thing but my heart goes out to them.
That sort of thing. That's what he said.
So there is a controversy about that.
Some historians said that you know
that's that's what it meant that he was
giving Assam up and other people said
that it's not the case. Whatever. So the
Chinese did reach parts of Assam
but then they withdrew and what's the
reason for that is what the question is.
So in 1962 we have to understand what
was the Chinese objective? What did they
seek to achieve in this war?
See at that time India's leader prime
minister was Mr. Nehu and China's
dictator was Shri Maatung. Mr. Maadong
now Mr. Nehu
was a self-styled statesman, global
statesman. He would go around the world
and give lectures to countries, moral
lectures
and uh he was the leader of the
non-aligned movement, one of the leaders
and so on. So the Chinese were very
annoyed and irritated with with this
approach and they could see that India's
economy was was was doing terribly under
the leadership of Shir Neuji. India was
India's growth rate was crawling. India
was not doing well at all. India was
being misgoverned and there were so many
problems in India but Mr. era was going
around as as a great world leader and
India's the Chinese probably knew that
India's armed forces were not you know
being supplied properly not being taken
care of properly by the government and
Indian armed forces were in a very
probably not in a very good shape and so
on right from the perspective of
supplies and ammunition and arms and
equipment and whatnot so the Chinese
said we need to teach India a lesson
that's what Mahatong intended in the war
he wanted to humiliate India teach India
a lesson and he wanted to humiliate Mr.
Neu.
That was the objective and obviously the
military objectives were to consolidate
China's occupation of Tibet and take
some more Indian territory.
So some Indian territory that Chinese
had already enclosed upon in the 1950s.
Akai Chin the Chinese built road a road
through Akachin and the government of
India did not know for a couple of
years. That's how deep the slumber was
in the Neu government. So they the
Chinese wanted to solidify their hold on
Axai Chin and probably nibble away at
some more Indian territory. So they
achieved all of that. They defeated the
Indian the Indian military because
India's military was very woefully
illequipped and the government the
Indian government refused to to use the
air force Indian air force for some
reason and so much more. I mean you can
read the book Himalayan blender which is
which is somewhere here in which you
will see all the details. Himalayan
blunder by brigadier JP Dalvey, John
Dalvi.
So the Chinese objective was to
humiliate India to defeat the Indian
army and to take more territory and to
humiliate Mr. Neru and they achieved all
of that and then they realized they've
taken they've taken too much territory
and they probably did not have any
intention of of holding more territory
than the parts of Tibet that they were
interested in because if you take on
more territory that then it it becomes a
kind of an additional burden because
you're occupying the territory you have
to place your armed forces there and the
people obviously don't like China. The
people are Indian. You may have to
pacify the people maybe all that stuff.
So it's complicated. The Chinese
probably wanted to only hold on to
Himalayan territory and the Tibetan
territory. And whatever parts of India
they regarded as strategically important
for them. Whatever they want to occupy,
they had captured and they most likely
had no objective of taking parts of
Assam or or the whole of Assam. So they
realized they had gone too far and they
withdrew to the lines that they had
predefined for themselves because they
had achieved their military and
political objectives. So that that's re
probably why that's the reasons why they
probably uh decided to withdraw from the
parts of Assam that they had encroached
into because they had achieved the
objectives they had set out to do and
this was more than that and they didn't
want this. That's what
Mrianka Seeker Visa says. Misoram is
biometrically enrolling over 35,000
refugees from Myanmar and Bangladesh.
What internal security risks does India
face and why is the government
permitting this? So if you if you go to
Google, okay, let's let's Google this.
What's happening? What what exactly is
going on? Misoram
refugees.
Miso
miso ram
refugees
bio
metric let's see this misor this is from
one day ago misoram launches biometric
enrollment for 33,000 refugees from
Myanmar in Bangladesh
okay 33,000 refugees
are currently taking shelter in all 11
districts of misoram
2,000 something are from Chitagong hill
tracks in southern Bangladesh, southeast
Bangladesh and the rest are from
Myanmar.
The refugees are mostly cooki cookies
mostly chin tribes also called cookies.
They have almost full ethnic and
cultural similarity with the majority
misos of misoram. So the misoram what's
happening is that misoram is giving
shelter to cookies who have come in from
Myanmar and coming from uh the chitagong
hill tracks region of Bangladesh cookies
right um is this being done with the
ascent
with the approval of the central
government or is the central government
kind of allowing this because this has
already happened. We also know that you
know it has been alleged very strongly
multiple times over and over again that
Misoram was was the conduit for pushing
in god knows how many laps lacks of
cookie infiltrators from from Burma into
Manipur right and now Mizoram is giving
I mean it is biometrically
enrolling 35 or 33,000 refugees I think
it's it's very concerning
allowing foreigners to squat on your
territory is extremely dangerous for
national security.
Uh what compulsions does the government
of India have? Like I've said, this
project Kukiland for Christ is a US
government project and the objective is
to create an artificial country. At
least that was the objective during the
Biden administration, Biden regime's
tenure to create an artificial nation
out of parts of Manipur, out of Misoram,
out of parts of Burma and parts of
Bangladesh, an artificial cookie
Christian nation.
And this was alleged, this this
allegation was made multiple times by
the prime minister of Bangladesh, not by
some some random journalist or whatever
news readader. This was made by the
prime minister of Bangladesh. So you've
got to take it very seriously. This was
a real thing. Project K cookie land for
Christ. And now what's the status of
that? We're not sure. But there there is
the involvement of the US in this this
entire cookie cookie issue. the the
foreigners who are now squatting in
Indian territory and occupying Indian
territory. So
and does the Misoram government have
connections? You know the the then chief
minister of miseram
I think on US territory he had said
something about reunifying with some
parts of Burma or something. I think
there's a clip of that on my channel
somewhere.
So I think there's a significant amount
of foreign hand in this and by foreign
hand we clearly mean the superpower
itself right so maybe there are some
compulsions right now but overall this
is a huge national security issue you
are allowing foreigners on your soil
foreigners who have no allegiance to the
government of India who have no
allegiance to the nation of India who
have no cultural affinity with India
and if they are squatting on on our
territory. It's a huge problem for us.
So I think at some point in time the
government of India will have to evict
every single foreigner from Indian
territory. Whether it is in Misoram,
whether it's in Manipur or wherever
else, expel them all, deport them all.
You don't have to put them on planes.
You just have to make them cross the
border back into Burma. That's it. Or
wherever else.
Okay. Rahul Dunak says, "Can simple
clapping of hands
cause gravitational waves? If they if if
it if it's if it's the case, then how
powerful should be the legal device to
make such a minuscule reading?" Simple
clapping of hands. Can the clapping of
hands cause gravitational waves? So if
you study general relativity you will
know that any kind of acceleration of
mass of a mass will cause gravitational
waves. Acceleration of mass which also
means deceleration. So when my hands are
at rest over here they are
stationary. Now when I clap it means my
hands accelerated towards each other and
then stopped which means decelerated. So
when you have when you have acceleration
and deceleration of a mass by hand mass
obviously then you're going to have
gravitational waves even this will cause
gravitational waves but these
gravitational waves are going to be
extraordinarily faint. The amplitudes
are going to be minuscule. What's the
amplitude? A wave has two things
frequency and amplitude. Right? If you
look at waves in water, they have
frequency, which means how how often per
second does does the waveform appear and
they have amplitude, which means how
tall are the waves. Amplitude and
frequency, how many times per second and
how tall are the waves. So,
gravitational waves are extremely
extremely faint,
which means they have very small
amplitudes. When two black holes collide
or merge or when a black hole collides
with a neutron star, that causes a
gravitational wave tsunami. Even that is
so faint that you need a four you know
something like LIGO whose arms which is
an interferometer with 4 kilometer arms
to barely measure the signal right so
when you have the clapping of hands you
can very quickly do a rough calculation
of the strain amplitude okay I'll not
tell you what that is because I to
explain physics then there's something
called strain amplitude you can estimate
that by just plugging in some numbers
let's say my two hands are have a mass
of 1 kilogram each. Let's say the
frequency is about 40 Hz of the clap and
so on. You can put in some some rough
numbers and that gives you uh typically
you know what kind of amplitude the wave
is going to have. So it gives you the
strain amplitude and you will find that
from that you can determine how large
the interferometer needs to be the
instrument LI legal like instrument has
to be. So for LIIGO the arms are 4 km
long roughly
if you were to create a LIGO kind of
instrument interferometer that can
measure the gravitational waves produced
by this clapping
you will find that the arms I did a
rough calculation before this this show
so you'll find that the arms of the
interferometer need to be between 40
million light years and 10 to 15 light
years in length each arm.
So
imagine an instrument whose arms are 40
million light years long each and they
are at a right angle to each other.
Right? The Milky Way, our galaxy, home
galaxy is about 100,000 one lakh light
years across in diameter. The nearest
galaxy Andromeda is about 2 and a half
million light years away. Right? But if
it's 40 million lighty years, that's
further than the Andromeda galaxy. And
if it's 10 to 15 light years, that's
bigger than the diameter of the
observable universe. So essentially what
I'm saying is that you can never build
an instrument that can detect the
gravitational waves that are caused by
the clapping of two hands. That's how
faint the gravitational waves are.
That's how that's how weak the
gravitational force is. Very interesting
thought experiment.
And Rahul asks a different question.
What's the difference between a twister,
a tornado and a hurricane? So, first of
all, a twister and a tornado is the same
thing. A twister is just a different
name, a more colloquial name for a
tornado. Tornado. Tornado. Tornado.
That's the Spanish way of saying
tornado. So, and what's a hurricane? A
hurricane and a tornado. Okay. So, we're
talking about two classes of of of
phenomena. Tornadoes and hurricanes.
Twister is the same as tornado. So both
of these phenomena are rotating storm
systems but they are very different in
the scale and size and formation and
whatnot. So hurricane what is a
hurricane in India we call it a cyclone.
Okay. So a hurricane or a cyclone is a
massive enormous storm system. Let's
let's take a look at Google. Okay. Let's
let's see an image of a cyclone or a
hurricane. A satellite image. They are
visible from satellite images.
hurricane. Okay. So, let's take a look
at this. So, over here you can see a
hurricane on of in the in the Gulf of
Mexico near Florida. This this over here
is Florida, this peninsula. And you can
see how large the hurricane is. It's
enormous. So, hurricanes are gigantic
storm systems that can span hundreds of
kilometers across in diameter and they
can affect entire coastlines. It can
affect entire regions. But if you look
at a tornado,
if you look at a tornado, it's a much
smaller storm sister system. Typically,
there will be tens of meters in
diameter. Sometimes a kilometer or two
in diameter. But these systems,
tornadoes, they are extremely
concentrated and intense storm systems.
So hurricanes, these things, they
typically form over warm ocean waters
and they require a specific set of
atmospheric conditions to form. Okay?
And these hurricanes, they can develop
over days or weeks. They develop slowly.
But tornadoes, they form from
thunderstorms, severe thunderstorms. And
they can meet they they can form in a
matter of minutes. They can form in
front of your eyes, right? And
hurricanes can last for days or weeks
sometimes. And they will move across
oceans. They will move across land.
Tornadoes will last for minutes or just
an hour. And hurricanes typically occur
over oceans and tornadoes generally
occur over land and so on and so forth.
So that's the essential difference
between a tor tornado and a hurricane.
Okay. Okay. N Ji Bora says, "What's your
views on the hope mission by ISRO? What
are the implications and what's the
possibility of the mission being a
success?" Hope mission. Let's let's
quickly Google it. It's it's a mission
designed to simulate the conditions that
you encounter when you're living on Mars
or possibly the moon. So, ISRO hope
and this is in in Lelay. Uh no, not in
Lelay, it's in Lada. So, this mission is
is happening in Ladak. Uh where do we
see which one do we see? Let's take a
look at this. Uh ISRO launches hope
mission in Ladak to simulate astronaut
life for Gaganyan.
It's a 10day high altitude mission
isolation mission. So you'll have this
sort of you know igloo kind of facility
in which you'll have some people who
will stay who will be isolated for a
certain number of time certain number
number of days. The Russians have and
the Americans have done such missions in
the past. So isolating astronauts on the
earth in simulated environments that uh
are similar to what you will find if
astronauts will be on the moon or on
Mars. And the Russians and Americans may
have done missions that are in excess of
one year long. This mission that we are
launching in Ladak, it's a 10-day
mission, high altitude isolation
mission. August one it was launched. So
it could get over in a couple of days
maybe. It's at 14,000 ft. It simulates
the extreme conditions that astronauts
might face on longduration space
missions to the moon or mars. It's part
of preparations for India's Gagyan human
space flight program and future
interplanetary exploration. There's a
twoperson crew. ISTRO has selected
somebody who's a PhD candidate at Purdue
University and somebody else who is a
planetary science graduate from the
University of Aberdine because maybe
Indian universities don't have anybody.
I don't know what's the deal. Anyhow, so
it's a mission that's designed to
simulate the conditions that astronauts
will face if they are on a mission to
the moon or Mars or maybe space
isolation and so on. It's good. Will the
mission be a success? Of course, it will
be a success. It's a 10-day mission.
Anybody can survive 10 days in isolation
with somebody else. But the real problem
is when you are when you are stuck with
somebody for a year or two. Let's say
you are traveling to Mars on a on a
space capsule or spacecraft with a with
let's say a threeperson crew. The travel
the the the voyage to Mars will
typically last about 9 10 months. Okay?
If it's during the launch window, the
optimum time to launch to Mars. So you
have three people who are in a small
capsule stuck with each other.
If you're stuck with somebody that you
don't get along with, it becomes a
nightmare. So you have to do
psychological profiling and what so much
more of each astronaut to see whether
they are compatible and they'll be able
to work well together and then you have
to prepare them for such missions by
doing things like this hope mission. So
you simulate the conditions of of a
space flight of a long space mission and
are you able to survive together in
isolation and get along together and do
all that's required and so on. So that
is what this mission is like this whole
mission. It's a 10-day mission.
Eventually in the future we'll have
longer missions that will happen. And
Ladak is a great environment for this
sort of mission. It's very isolated,
very few people there. Uh very uh very
harsh climatic conditions, high
altitude, whatnot. So it kind of
simulates be being stuck in space or you
know being on a mission to Mars or the
or the moon or something. So yeah, uh
it's great to see this happen.
Xiinping says, "What's your opinion on
the assassination of the last Morian
Empire by Pushchamitra Suna? Did
Pushamitra Suna Shunga really persecute
Buddhists?" So the last Morian emperor,
his name was Brihadrata Moria and his
commanderin-chief, his sinapathi was
this gentleman called Pushutra. Pushy
Mitra Shunga
and during a military parade
Push Push Mitra Shunga assassinated
Brihadra Brihadrat Moria and took over
the leadership of the empire.
So I believe Pushitraunga's
justification for this was that the
emperor was not carrying out his duties.
He was running the empire into the
ground. The empire was in trouble. You
had Greek invaders who typically were
were uh ruling in Gandhar because of the
u because of the uh consequences of uh
of the Seucid Empire being in that
region. So there was a pact there was a
treaty formal treaty alliance between
the Moria Empire and the Seucid Empire
and after the dissolution of the Seucid
Empire. um the the the governors that
they had left behind in the western part
of Gandhar, they became kings in the in
their own right and eventually they
became more powerful and when the Moria
empire declined the Greeks started
making inroads further eastwards into
India itself from the outskirts of
Gandhar all the way into India itself
and push Bush Mitraunga said that the
the last Moria empire was not doing his
job in safeguarding the country. So he
assassinated assassinated breedatraia
and became the emperor of India. But
Pushiaunga never called himself emperor.
He always called himself synapati even
when he was ruling the country. And he
did fight a significantly long war with
the indoeks and defeated them. So good
job sir. Good job. So that's how it
goes. You know did pushyraunga really
persecute Buddhists? Well, if you look
at Buddhist Buddhist texts, they say
that he was bad and he was he persecuted
both the dharma and all that. But if you
look at if you look at it from an
independent perspective, neutral
perspective, most likely it's because
Pusha Mutra Shunga was no longer giving
all the free benefits and all that the
Buddhists were getting from Brihadrata
Moria. Pushut did not persecute
Buddhists, but he just stopped stopped
giving them freebies and and special
treatment, preferential treatment. Then
you have texts written by a Sri Lanka by
by by the king of Lanka at the time
whose name I forget in which it's it's
very clear that you know Buddhist
monasteries and stupers and all that
were flourishing just as well in India
during the time when Pushia Mitra was
the emperor and you even had uh
embassies from Subarabumi which is
Thailand the Southeast Asia region who
had come to India with with donations to
create Buddhist supers the they were
allowed to do that by pushing. So these
allegations that Pushy Mitrunga was a
brahminical tyrant and oppressor of
Buddhists, it's a lie. It's a lie.
Fabrication.
All right. Bully
Bully Palish Bully Pali Ashish says,
"What was Russia's religion before
Christianity?" I Googled and it says
Slavic paganism.
um that says that Slavic paganism was
followed followed which which is a
polytheistic religion. If Russia was not
invaded by any country like South Korea
or Japan, how did the religion change
gradually? Similarly, how will India
continue its own religion without
succumbing to other religious forces
that are looming uh onto the people and
their mindsets? Okay. Slavic paganism.
That's correct. What was Slavic
paganism? Slavic paganism was a subset
of European paganism. What was European
paganism? It was nothing but the
European version of the old Indo-Uropean
religion which is the Vic religion.
It's the same thing. If you look at
religion h let's call it Hinduism. If
you look at the way Hinduism is
practiced in India in different parts of
India it's very different manifestations
of Hinduism very different gods and
goddesses looks like there's no
connection but it's all connected right?
We understand that in India we are a
very diverse country. The kind of
Hinduism that's practiced in Assam is
very different from what's practiced in
Manipur. It's very different from what's
practiced in Maharashtra, very different
from what's practiced in Punjab, very
different from what's practiced in Tamil
Nadu and so on so forth.
Very different manifestations of the
same religion, same culture, same
civilization. Similarly, you had the old
Indo-Uropean religion all the way from
the western boundaries of India all the
way to Ireland.
Polytheism,
the same gods p worshiped under
different names.
The Slavs they had a god god called
Perun who the same as Pjana a Vic god uh
the Irish their mother goddess was Danu
the river goddess who was a rigidic
river goddess so much more but here's an
interesting thing let me show you
something very interesting so the Slavs
okay they had this god called
thri
so this is a Slavic god threeheaded god
Okay, three heads whose name is Trilav.
Now if you go down, if you look at the
details
of Triglav. So Serbian folk tradition
says that Trilav is the holy trinity. It
means that for Serbs, Trilav is the holy
God, father, son, and holy spirit. Okay,
that's a very Abrahamic interpretation
of of of this deity.
Now
in Serbian mythology, Trilav consists of
Vishni, Zea and Brahanj.
The Holy Trinity, Vishni, Zea and
Braanjan. It sounds like Branjan,
Vishni and Shiva. It's essentially the
same thing as Shiva, Vishnu and Brahma,
right? And Serbian folk tradition says
that Trilav lives in India. in India was
was the home of the Serbs and Serbs had
to leave because of a huge political
upheaval of some kind. Sounds like a war
between many kings.
Very ancient folk memories, right? We
don't know the time of migration from
India to Europe and all that. Very very
ancient memories are still preserved in
these folk traditions in Europe. So the
Serbs are a Slavic people. The Russians
are the major Slavic people. So they
they practiced the old religion which is
the which is just a European version of
the old Vic religion. Okay. Um that's
what it was before Christianity. Russia
was not invaded but you know there were
invasions. There were the northern
crusades. It's a long story long brutal
story of the imposition of Christianity
across Europe. It was imposed by force.
It was hammered into the minds and
practices of the people. It was done by
force. You had northern crusades. You
had other crusades. crusades not just
against what they called uter which is
uh uh which which is the present day
Israel region but crusades against
Europeans themselves very brutal very
very bloody crusades against Europeans
and that's how step by step Christian
Christianity was imposed upon the people
of Europe and the same thing happened in
Russia and there was tremendous
resistance to the imposition of
Christianity especially among the Slavic
people until the 18th 19th century you
had resistance against the imposition of
Christianity and even today to a large
extent the Slavic people some of them
practice very superficial Christianity
with very deep elements of the prech
Christian uh native religion of the
Slavic people
very long story very interesting story
as well um and if you want to know how
Christianity was imposed upon the people
of Europe I would say I would say read
the book by Katherine Nixie right the
darkening age I have it somewhere I'll
show it some other day. Um similarly,
how will India continue its own religion
without succumbing to other religious
forces that are trying to yeah intrude
upon the country and the people? Well,
in India, see our religion, our culture
needs state support. It dies without
state support. We we will have people
practicing it at various levels. But it
it truly flourishes only when you have
state support in India. And
historically, our kings emperors, they
provided state support to our culture
and religion. Right now India is a
secular country. That's why that's why
our culture is slowly withering's way.
So something will have to be done about
that. We will need better governments, a
better system of governance perhaps.
Yeah. Okay. Let's take a couple of
questions more. Um Anu Bhavika says
happy Rakshaman. Well, happy Rakshaman
to you also and everybody else is
watching. Happy Rakshamand. I am
currently pursuing BDS Bachelor of
Balorate in dental dental surgery
perhaps dental surgeon UG undergraduate
from a government college in India. Is
dentistry a waste in India? Like as said
by many others, what are your views?
Should I stay in India or search for
foreign opportunities? I love my
country. Don't don't want to go abroad
and so on. Um India has a population of
1.4 billion people and our dietary
habits are changing. Indians are now
beginning to adopt the dietary habits of
people in the west. Lots of sweet
products, lots of lots of processed
foods and all which is causing
tremendous problems, dental problems in
India's population. I think for a
dentist, India should be a heaven.
If you have your own private practice in
some part in some city or some some town
of wherever you're going to have a
lifelong supply of customers. I don't
think dentistry is a waste in India. I
don't think so. I think there's there's
huge there's going to be a huge scope
for dentistry practice in India.
Dentists will always have work to do. Um
in the west of course if you stay there
you you earn a lot more money. No
question about it. But you won't have as
many people coming to you as you will
have in India. So I think you know uh if
you really prefer to stay in India,
you'll do just well in India. You'll do
great in India. Uh my views about
whether you should stay in India or look
for foreign opportunities. It's entirely
up to you. I tell people that go and
go go wherever you are treated best.
Many people ask me should I stay in
India and serve the country or should I
go abroad and and uh earn elsewhere. I
would say
I would say that you should go wherever
you are able to rise to the fullest
extent of your potential. If you really
love India know serve India go abroad
spend 20 30 years there go and become
very wealthy then then come back to
India and then then invest your wealth
in India. If you are just starting off
you have no and you have no money you
can't serve India better go abroad earn
a tremendous amount of money then come
back to India with that money and and
then invest that money in the right
places in India. So I would say it's up
to you if you get good opportunities
abroad and if you if you think that
that's something you should explore I
would say certainly go ahead explore
foreign opportunities
it doesn't mean that you don't love your
country if you go abroad right but if
you don't want to go abroad I think you
will do just fine in India so it's
entirely up to you all the best ma'am
all the best
and pra says this is not a geopolitics
question which is fine I've watched your
announcement about the future strategy
for the channel you're First, you're the
reason I first discovered geopolitics
and since then you've been a rock rock
solid pillar in my learning journey as
someone curious yet facing many life
challenges. I want to ask when you first
realized the issue that led to this
change, what was your immediate reaction
and how did you tackle it to swiftly
move forward and aim higher in a new
direction? Many of us face obstacles,
but it's often the speed and clarity of
our decisions that define our lives. If
possible, please share how you
approached this turning point. I'll
always well thank you so much sir first
of all thank you so much I really
appreciate that uh you asked great
questions so I really like those um so
my announcement yesterday was about me
ending the geost strategy podcast the
geo strategy series and the Indian
interest series and
and what happened so it's been a couple
of months since I started this and from
the very beginning I saw that the
platform which is YouTube was uh hitting
those videos with limited ads it means
that ads will not be served or very
limited ads will be served on those
videos. Well, that is not a problem. I
don't care whether ads are running or
not on the videos as long as the videos
are being viewed, right? I'm not in this
for making money from the videos. Money
comes, I have no issue with that. But if
if you YouTube wants to limit the ads,
that's fine. But from the first episode
itself, it was hit with limited ads. And
every other most of the other episodes
were also hit with limited ads
immediately and the views obviously were
very very low and people are have been
saying for a long time they're not
getting notifications or whatever. So it
looks like there is some kind of action
being taken against um about the channel
and the kind of content I'm putting out.
So it became very clear after time. So I
thought you know what I've just started
this this series geo strategy. I've also
restarted Indian interest. Let's
continue for a while and let's see let's
see the pattern in the data. You have to
let data drive your decisions. So after
15 episodes I've seen that there's a
very clear consistent pattern that uh
the videos are being hit with limited
ads and maybe it's a message being sent
to me you know so you've got to heed the
message. Uh so that's why I decided that
okay let's take this ch let's make this
uh choice and end this series. I can
still write articles about geo
geopolitics on a new website and I can
put out everything over there and
whoever wants to uh take a look at it
read it they can do it. So that's why I
made the announcement. So um I first let
some data come to me. I did this for a
couple of months even though from the
very first day I noticed what was
happening. So I gave it some time and
once the p pattern was established
beyond any doubt whatsoever I said okay
fine let's quickly take the
necessary steps in the right direction.
And I anyway had all these pending book
projects and all. So I s I said that
okay I'll I'll now focus on that and
I'll focus on my writing. It's been a
long time since I've written seriously
and it's something that is actually
I am primarily a writer more than a
speaker. So you know it's it's good to
go get back to that and uh so that's why
I made the decision. So when you're
faced with so it's all about turning
difficulties into opportunities.
I'm having to end this but I can use
that opportunity to to pivot to
something else and make it also
productive and and hopefully useful. So
it's all about u using opportunity using
difficulties and turning them into
opportunities and always always be
positive always always find a solution
to whatever problems you're facing. So
that's that's always been my approach to
things. Right? That brings me to the end
of today's of the of the questions I
selected for today. Uh let me take a
couple of questions from the live chat.
Let's take a couple of questions. What
do we have on the live chat?
Uh let us see. Let us see. First of all,
Ankit G. Thank you very much. Really
appreciate that. Uh I have some Okay,
what what is this? Mlevin says Trump got
the leaders of Armenia and Azarbaijan to
sign peace agreements. Do you think it
will last? How will Turkey and Israel
react to this? I I haven't yet seen the
contents of this agreement. What is the
what are the terms of the agreement? Is
it a peace agreement and so on? We'll
have to see about that. Do I think it'll
last? I don't think it'll last forever.
Trump is is going to be in power for
two, three more years. Three and a half
more years, right? Three more years.
Three and a half. What happens after
that? We'll have to see. Trump is going
to be there for a while and then he's
going to be gone and he he cannot become
president for a third time. So then
maybe something else happens. So, I
think it's a temporary thing, but I
haven't really really seen the terms of
the agreement, so I don't know yet.
Okay.
Um, Heny Penguin says, "How are you,
sir?" Well, I'm doing very well. How you
doing?
Uh, right. Okay.
Mlevin says, "Donald Trump gets no prize
for forming RAC." All right. Let's give
him a Let's give him the prize for that.
Absolutely.
Um
okay
Shrida says what about the buffer state
Nepal
uh and its monarchy is there a chance
for coup in Nepal what will be the
impact on India look I don't see Nepal
as a buffer state I see it as as our
civilizational brother state and uh
what's the chance of a coup in Nepal
what will be the impact be on India the
chance of a coup in Nepal I I I don't
know is there a chance of a coup in
Nepal. The current go government
there's been this demand for for a
restoration of of the monarchy in Nepal
and and a lot of lot of people want
Nepal to to return to its original form
which is a Hindu nation. Um will that
happen? Will that be the reason for a a
coup?
Is monarchy potentially going to come
back? We I I don't know. Right now it
looks like there is
less of a chance of these things
happening.
Okay. Um,
have you seen the show Dark? I haven't
seen the show Dark. I haven't. I I hear
it's science fiction of some kind. I
haven't seen it. Don't have time to
watch stuff, unfortunately. I would love
to.
Is the world moving towards a bifocation
of the world order? Can things go back
to normal after Trump Trump leaves? No.
I think what Trump will the changes
Trump will do are going to be permanent
changes. they're going to totally
transform the world order. Um things
that is that he has set in motion are be
are going to be very hard to undo. For
example, the the relationship between
India and the US that's altered
permanently. That whatever trust India
may have had or may have developed over
the past 20 30 years it's disappeared.
It's disappeared after Trump's actions
with Pakistan.
So is it a bifurcation of the world
order thing right now? It's a
multi-polar world order but depending on
how things go between India, China or
Russia, there could be a bifurcation
also. So it may be multipolarity or it
may be bipolarity of some kind. We'll
have to see. It will all depend on what
happens in the next few months by the
end of this year potentially.
Okay.
Okay. I'm I'm going to end this now. We
have crossed 2 hours in 10 minutes. So
let me end this session over here. And
tomorrow I'm going to have another live
stream. It's going to be a super chat
live stream only geopolitics tomorrow.
So please go ahead and ask your
questions as many as you want tomorrow
and we'll take it forward. All right.
Thank you so much everybody. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards
and I will see you in the next live
stream. Take care. Good night. Good day.
Bye-bye. See you soon.